Finding Aid for St. Timothy’s Episcopal Church, Detroit, Mich., records, 1928-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
St. Timothy’s Episcopal Church, Detroit, Mich., records 1928-2010
St. Timothy’s Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.)
1 oversize folders
17 oversize volumes
7 linear feet
2012126 Ba 2; Ba Outsize
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were transferred from the Episcopal Church, Diocese of Michigan (donor no. 1059 ) and came to the library in 2012.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
St. Timothy's Episcopal Church, which ceased operation in 2010, was formed from the merger of St. Timothy's and St. Augustine's in 1968. Each church had been experiencing a significant decline in membership in the years prior to the merger.
The two churches were established at about the same time. St. Timothy's was established in (1928) as a store-front church in Detroit. St. Augustine's was established in 1929 following a survey taken by the Vicar of St. Cyprian's of the homes along 8 Mile Road in northwest Detroit and in the suburb of Inkster, west of Dearborn. St. Augustine's was intended to minister to the African American community in this area.
The records of St. Timothy's, transferred to the library following its dissolution, include registers, record books, and other materials from both St. Timothy's and from St. Augustine's (prior to the merger.
The bulk of the records relate to St. Timothy's and include parish registers with records of communicants, baptisms, confirmations, burials, and marriages; registers of church services; treasurer's record books; record books containing names of members and record of their giving; vestry minutes; subject files; church newsletters and bulletins, and photographs and a videotape.
The records of St. Augustine's date from 1929 to 1968. These records include a parish register and a register of church services, and a file of correspondence and other papers of the Rev. E.D. Morisseau.
Subjects:
African American churches--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.)--Church history.; Episcopal Church--Michigan--Detroit.; St. Augustine's Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.); St. Timothy's Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.)
Contributors:
St. Augustine's Episcopal Church (Detroit, Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- St. Augustine's
  - Correspondence and other papers of Rev. E.D. Morisseau (Box 1)
  - Confirmation records 1960-1967 (Box 1)
  - Parish register (include communicants, baptisms, confirmations, burials, marriages) 1929-1968 (mainly 1929-1967) (Volume 12)
  - Register of Church Services 1945-1967 (Volume 1)
- St. Timothy's Church Records
  - Articles of incorporation and related documents (Box 1)
  - Annual reports 1955-2008 (Box 1)
    (include some gaps)
  - Parish register (include communicants, baptisms, confirmations, burials, marriages)
    (dates vary within each category)
    - 1928-1951 (Box 1)
    - 1928-1952 (Volume 13)
    - 1939-1951 (Volume 14)
    - 1952-1965 (mainly 1952-1959 (Volume 15)
    - 1960-1968 (Volume 16)
    - 1968-2010 (Volume 17)
  - Marriage -- Statement of Intention 1970s-1980s (Box 1)
  - Baptism -- Information blank application 1960s-1990s (Box 1)
  - Confirmation -- Information blank application 1950s-1980s (Box 1)
  - Funeral programs 1980s-2010, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Register of Church Services
    - 1928-1936 (Box 2)
    - 1937-1958 (Volume 2)
    - 1958-1960 (Box 2)
    - 1960-1964 (Box 2)
    - 1964-1972 (Box 2)
    - 1972-1978 (Box 2)
    - 1978-1988 (Box 2)
  - Parochial reports to the Diocese 1973-1994, 19 folders (Box 2)
    (some gaps)
  - Financial records (receipts and disbursements) 1953-2009 (scattered records), 10 folders (Box 3)
  - Treasurer's Record Book
    (include record of cash received and disbursed; member's name with record of giving)
    - 1930 (Box 3)
    - 1931 (Volume 3)
    - 1932 (Box 3)
    - 1933 (Box 3)
    - 1934 (Box 3)
    - 1935 (Box 3)
    - 1936 (Box 3)
    - 1937 (Box 3)
    - 1938 (Box 3)
    - 1939 (Box 3)
  - Record books containing name of member and record of giving
    - 1950 (Volume 4)
    - 1951 (Volume 5)
    - 1952 (Volume 6)
    - 1953 (Volume 7)
    - 1954 (Volume 8)
    - 1955 (Volume 9)
    - 1956 (Volume 10)
    - 1957 (Volume 11)
  - Vestry minutes and agenda
    - 1988 1990-2010, 22 folders (Box 4)
  - Membership materials
    - Letters of transfer, A-Y, 21 folders (Box 5)
    - Membership card file, photocopies of cards (Box 5)
    - Directories and members and staff 1956-1967 (scattered), 8 volumes (Box 5)
    - Pastoral record of members, names and addresses, M-Z only (Box 5)
  - Topical files (unprocessed)
    - Church bulletins, newsletters, history and anniversary materials; office logs of visitors, phone calls, and notable events (Box 6)
  - Photographs of church activities and groups (Box 7)
    (See also oversize folder Ba Out.)
  - Videotape (VHS): 60th anniversary celebration, 3 copies (Box 7)
  - Citations, awards, testimonials, etc. (Folder Ba)